A Finding Aid to the Architectural League of New York Records, 1880s-1974, bulk 1927-1968, in the Archives of American Art AAA.archleag
Archives of American Art
Architectural League of New York records
1880s-1974
AAA.archleag
Archives of American Art
115.1 Linear feet
The records of the Architectural League of New York measure 115.1 linear feet and date from 1880s-1974 (bulk 1927-1968). The League's mission "to advance the art of architecture" is documented through administrative and business records, committee records and officers' files, exhibition files, records of functions and events, correspondence, publicity files, photographs, lantern slides, and 16 scrapbooks.
Architectural League of New York.
Provenance
The Architectural League of New York records were donated in several installments from 1967-1980 by the Architectural League of New York.
Related Material
Among the holdings of the Archives of American Art are several collections that contain Architectural League of New York records. The American Federation of Arts records, 1895-1993, include a significant amount of League records related to national awards programs and lantern slides from the "New Horizons in America" lecture series.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Historical Note
Modeling the organization's name after the Art Students League of New York, the Architectural League of New York was founded in New York City in 1881 by a group of architects who wished to gather and discuss architecture and its relationship to the arts. The group elected D.W. Willard as the first President of the League and they began gathering regularly to discuss and critique each other's sketches and hold competitions. The organization grew quickly and soon the League rented a room in a building on 14th Street between University Place and Fifth Avenue.
However, by the mid-1880s the founders and more active League members left New York, and membership began to falter. The League was reorganized in 1886, expanding membership beyond professional architects, and incorporated in 1888 with 166 members. In 1889, the League joined with the Art Students League of New York and the Society of American Artists to form the American Fine Arts Society. Thus, in 1892 the three organizations were able to erect a building at 215 West 57th Street where the League remained until 1927 when it moved to 115 East 40th Street.
The League was run by the Executive Committee and its officers, elected every two years. The beginning of each League season kicked off with an annual dinner in the spring. The League also formed numerous committees to organize activities and manage administrative tasks. Noteworthy committees include the Current Work Committee, House Committee, Finance Committee, Exhibition Committee, Membership Committee, and Scholarships and Special Awards Committee.
The League's interdisciplinary approach to architecture and the arts was expressed through sponsored forums and discussions with architects and artists. From the League's beginning, the Current Work Committee was established to organize educational forums for members. Recognition of achievement was awarded by an Annual Exhibition from the late 1880s until 1938. In 1950, the League began awarding the annual National Gold Medal Exhibition in various fields such as landscape architecture, engineering, and sculpture. Additionally, the League awarded numerous other scholarships each year. Architects, artists, and arts-related organizations could also rent space in the League building to hold meetings, discussions, and exhibitions.
The League admitted its first female member in 1934. Notable members of the League included Arnold W. Brunner (President, 1903-1905), Cass Gilbert (President, 1913-1915), Philip Johnson, Robert A.M. Stern, and Russell Sturgis (President, 1889-1893).
The Architectural League of New York continues to provide educational opportunities and scholarships to students and professionals.
Background information was gathered from a written history of the League by Cass Gilbert found in this collection and the Architectural League of New York website (http://archleague.org/category/archive/history-archive/).
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Architectural League of New York measure 115.1 linear feet and date from 1880s-1974 (bulk 1927-1968). The League's mission "to advance the art of architecture" is documented through administrative and business records, committee records and officers' files, exhibition files, records of functions and events, correspondence, publicity files, photographs, lantern slides, and scrapbooks.
League records prior to 1927 are limited in the collection and are mostly found among Administrative Files. The administrative files include a nearly complete collection of annual reports from 1889-1932 and various meetings minutes from 1889 through the mid-20th century. Also found is a history of the League written by founding member Cass Gilbert, documentation of the changes of the League Constitution and By-Laws during the first half of the 20th century, and other administrative records.
Over a third of the collection are records from committees, including voluminous records of the Executive Committee, Current Work Committee, House Committee, Finance Committee, Membership Committee, and Scholarships and Special Awards Committee. In addition, there are scattered records for minor committees. Materials include correspondence, meeting minutes, election ballots, financial records, membership records, documents related to awarding scholarships and awards, and other administrative and organizational committee records. Found is the original 1889 agreement between the Architectural League, the Art Students League, and the Society of American Artists to build the American Fine Arts Society building. Throughout the collection, but especially in the Membership Committee subseries, the records provide a glimpse into the struggles the League faced during the Depression through World War II to maintain dues-paying members.
Officers' Files includes collated records of the League Executive Secretary and Secretary, as well as correspondence of the League President and Treasurer. Materials found here are not comprehensive; similar materials can be found throughout the collection.
Financial records such as bank statements, correspondence, and ledgers; insurance correspondence and policies; and legal correspondence, are found in the Business Records series. This series does not include records prior to 1926.
Exhibition files provide detailed documentation of the exhibitions sponsored by, or held at, the League primarily from the 1930s to the early 1970s. Records related to the League Annual Exhibition, the National Gold Medal Exhibitions, and the 1939 World's Fair in New York are found here, as well as exhibition files arranged chronologically by exhibition date and miscellaneous administrative files. Materials include administrative files, applications, correspondence, printed materials, publicity files, and other records related to organizing and managing exhibitions. The files of the Exhibition Committee are also found here.
Other series which document activities held by, or held at, the League include Functions and Events series and Publicity Files series. Found is correspondence, printed materials, press releases, schedules, and other administrative documents created in organizing events such as dinners, lectures, receptions, balls, and outings. The Records of Other Organizations includes records relating to organizations that had business with the League, often regarding events, meetings, and exhibitions held at the League. Represented here are some records of the American Institute of Architects (A.I.A.) and the National Sculpture Society (N.S.S.).
Correspondence includes miscellaneous correspondence arranged alphabetically by subject or name, and collated correspondence arranged chronologically. Most of the chronological correspondence appears to be Secretaries' files. The materials in the Miscellaneous series seem to have been separated from their original files, or were never filed properly. Therefore, materials and contents are similar to those found in other series, such as correspondence, administrative records, some financial records, and handwritten notes.
Black and white photographs, a handful of colored photographs, nearly 350 lantern slides, and negatives of exhibitions, buildings, events, and portraits are found in the Photographic Materials series.
Sixteen scrapbooks include eight scrapbooks of clippings from 1880s-1960s, and seven scrapbooks of notices and printed materials from 1925-1930. Also found is a scrapbook of signatures of event attendees, a clippings scrapbook compiled by Hamilton M. Wright, and a scrapbook of the Archeological Institute of America.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 12 series:
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1889-1969 (Boxes 1-10, OV 116; 9.7 linear feet)
Series 2: Committee Records, 1887-1974 (Boxes 10-54, 110, 114, OV 116; 44.7 linear feet)
Series 3: Officers' Files, 1900, 1923-1970 (Boxes 54-58; 3.9 linear feet)
Series 4: Business Records, circa 1926-1972 (Boxes 58-62, BVs 129-144; 7.35 linear feet)
Series 5: Exhibitions, 1887-1972, bulk 1930s-1960s (Boxes 62-83, 111, OVs 117-119; 21.85 linear feet)
Series 6: Functions and Events, 1909, 1931-1973 (Boxes 84-93, OV 120; 9.35 linear feet)
Series 7: Publicity Files, 1922-1972 (Boxes 93-95, 111; 2.5 linear feet)
Series 8: Records Relating to Organizations, 1908-1968, bulk 1930s-1960s (Boxes 95-101; 6.1 linear feet)
Series 9: Correspondence, 1929-1970 (Boxes 101-103, OV 120; 1.85 linear feet)
Series 10: Miscellaneous, circa 1936-1968 (Boxes 103-104; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 11: Photographic Materials, 1896-1960s (Boxes 105-108, 112, OVs 121-128; 4.3 linear feet)
Series 12: Scrapbooks, 1880s-1960s (Boxes 108-109, 113-115, BVs 145-148; 2.2 linear feet)
There are frequently similar and related materials in multiple series, as is indicated in the series' descriptions. The records may originally have been arranged by file owner (committees, secretary, etc.), then by League season (roughly May - April). Most series include a handful of folders in which the original folder title indicates the file owner and League season (i.e. Secretary 1938-1939).
American Institute of Architects.; Gilbert, Cass, 1859-1934; National Sculpture Society (U.S.); New York World's Fair (1939-1940).; Annual reports; Architecture; Associations, institutions, etc.; Lantern slides; Minutes; Photographs; Scrapbooks
- Administrative Files, 1889-1969; Series 1; 9.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-10, OV 116
  Scope and Contents note
  Administrative Files includes a nearly complete run of annual reports from 1889-1932 (not present: 1890-1891, 1892-1893, 1895-1896, 1898-1899, 1899-1900); League meeting minutes and various committee meeting minutes collated and arranged chronologically; records and notes regarding changes in the League Constitution and By-Laws; vendor receipts; some Secretary's files from the late 1920s-1943; a history of the League written by founding member Cass Gilbert, and other administrative records.
  Arrangement note
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - 115 East 40th Street Available Space, 1953; (Oversized material housed in OV 116) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 115 East 40th Street Building Plans, 1927; (Oversized material housed in OV 116) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 115 East 40th Street Proposed Changes, 1946; (Oversized material housed in OV 116) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Meeting (Apr. 5, 1951), Reports of Committees (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Meeting (Apr. 28, 1965) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Meeting Dinner, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports, 1889-1932; (8 folders) (Box 1, Folder 7-14)
  - Annual Reports, 1889-1932; (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
  - Annual Reports, 1889-1932; (7 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
  - Annual Reports, 1889-1932; (6 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
  - Annual Reports, 1889-1932; (5 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - Annual Reports, 1940-1941, 1947-1948, 1955; (5 bound volumes) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Architects Offices, Inc., 1927, 1942-1952 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Architects Offices, Inc., 1927-1962; (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
  - Catalog, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files (Box 6)
    - 1934-1951, 1960-1962, Executive Committee Minutes, (16 folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-16)
    - 1940-1943, 1948-1949, Scholarships and Special Awards Committee Minutes (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - 1945 Proceedings of the Architectural League of New York (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - 1946 Proceedings, Joint Meeting - ALNY and Municipal Art Society (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - 1949-1959, Various Committee Minutes, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 20-21)
  - Chronological Files (Box 7)
    - 1950-1953, Various Committee Minutes, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - 1951-1963, Various Committee Minutes, 1949-1963; (18 folders) (Box 7, Folder 3-20)
  - Chronological Files (Box 8)
    - 1951-1963, Various Committee Minutes, 1949-1963; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - 1955-1967, Membership Lists of Committees (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Constitution and By-Laws (1951) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Constitution and By-Laws (Box 8)
    - Amendments, 1918, 1937-1943, 1950s; (8 folders) (Box 8, Folder 5-12)
    - Amendments and Correspondence (1960-1961) (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - By-Laws Committee Correspondence, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Changes, circa 1947, 1949; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 15-16)
    - Changes - J. Scott Williams, 1937-1960 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Data (1955-1956), circa 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Draft Article IV Membership, undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Notated, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Old, 1951-1955 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Proposed Amendment to Article 2, Section 1, Dues and Charges, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Proposed Amendments, 1938-1964; (4 folders) (Box 8, Folder 23-26)
    - Proposed Amendments and Letters, 1922-1924, 1953; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 27-28)
    - Proposed By-Laws Correspondence, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Proposed Changes (1953), 1934-1955 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Guest Register, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - History of the Founding, 1921-1958 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Minutes of Annual Meetings, 1950-1969; (4 folders) (Box 8, Folder 33-36)
  - Minutes of Regular Meetings, 1889-1917; (4 folders) (Box 8, Folder 37-40)
  - Minutes of Regular Meetings, 1889-1917; (10 folders) (Box 9, Folder 1-10)
  - Minutes of Special Meeting (Dec. 4, 1917) (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Notices, Miscellaneous, 1946-1963 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Overview of Arch League of NY for A.I.A. 1965 Citation of an Organizational Medal, 1950s-1965 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Proceedings, 1899; (2 bound volumes) (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Ration Statements and Books, 1942-1946; (3 folders) (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
  - Rationing, 1943-1944 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Receipts, circa 1938-1966; (14 folders) (Box 10, Folder 5-18)
  - Secretary 1929-1930, Affidavits of Mailing Amendment to Increase Dues (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Secretary 1933-1934, Constitution and By-Laws, Proposed Amendements (Notices Sent 4/19/34) (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Secretary 1933-1934, Proposed Important Changes in The League - A.L. Harmon, President, 1933-1935 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Secretary 1937-1938, Constitution and By-Laws, Amendments Proposed by Membership (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Secretary 1938-1939, Annual Meeting, Reports of Committee Chairmen (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Secretary 1938-1939, Annual Meeting, Requests for Reports, 1939-1940 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Secretary 1939-1940, [Annual Meeting], Notices of Committee Meetings (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Secretary 1939-1940, [Annual Meeting], Reports of Committees (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Secretary 1940-1941, Annual Meeting, Requests and Presentation of Committee Reports (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Secretary 1941-1943, Annual Meeting, Reports (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Secretary 1941-1943, Annual Meeting, Requests for Reports, 1942-1943 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - 115 East 40th Street Available Space, 1953; (Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 1) (Box OV 116)
  - 115 East 40th Street Building Plans, 1927; (Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 2) (Box OV 116)
  - 115 East 40th Street Proposed Changes, 1946; (Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 3) (Box OV 116)
- Committee Records, 1887-1974; Series 2; 44.7 Linear feet Boxes 10-54, 110, 114, OV 116
  Committee Records includes files created in the course of the daily work of varying League committees. Exhibition Committee records are found in the Exhibitions series.
  The series is arranged as 7 subseries:
  2.1: Executive Committee, 1887-1973
  2.2: Current Work Committee, 1927-1972
  2.3: House Committee, 1889-1969
  2.4: Finance Committee, 1895-1972
  2.5: Membership Committee, 1897-1972
  2.6: Scholarships and Special Awards Committee, 1927-1973
  2.7: Various Committees, 1905-1974
  - Executive Committee, 1887-1973; 2.1
    The Executive Committee subseries documents the activities of the Executive Committee through meeting minutes and notes from 1887-1970; correspondence; Secretary's Files, and other records created in the course of the committee's work overseeing the League. Found is one sound tape reel for a January 28, 1960 meeting.
    - 1961 Contingency Fund Resolution (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Action Committee Minutes, circa 1969 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - American Institute of Architects, Bulletins, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Annual Meetings, 1965-1969 (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Answers to Requests for Information, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - Appointments by Executive Committee, 1943, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 35)
    - Budgets, House, circa late 1950s-1960s (Box 10, Folder 36)
    - City Planning Commission News, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 37)
    - City Walls, Inc., 1969 (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence, General, 1949-1973; (9 folders) (Box 10, Folder 39-47)
    - Correspondence (Box 11)
      - Bills, Etc., 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Fine Arts Federation, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Louis Lobell Co. Insurance, 1969-1971 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - President, 1967-1969 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Stolen Sculpture, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Executive Committee Members, 1941-1973 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Expense Report Sheets [Blank], circa 1960s (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - First Newsletter, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - For Next Executive Committee Meeting, 1941, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Invitations to Join Executive Committee, 1943, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - L.A. Pedrick, Executive Committee Papers, Etc., 1947-1948 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - League Relocation, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Legal Problems, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Letters to Executive Committee Members, 1947-1973 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Letters to Executive Committee Members, Baylinson Proposal, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Letters to Officers Regarding Minutes, 1949-1950 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Meeting (January 28, 1960), (1 sound tape reel) (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Meeting Agendas, 1948-1953, 1962-1967; (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 18-19)
    - Meeting Notes (Handwritten), 1917-1921; (Material restricted due to preservation concerns) (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Minor Bishop Book, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Minutes of Executive Committee Meetings, 1887-1933; (9 folders, Separated materials housed in Box 114, Folder 1) (Box 11, Folder 22-30)
    - Minutes of Executive Committee Meetings, 1887-1933; (10 folders) (Box 12, Folder 1-10)
    - Minutes of Executive Committee Meetings, 1887-1933; (3 folders) (Box 13, Folder 1-3)
    - Minutes of Executive Committee Meetings, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Minutes of Executive Committee Meetings, 1941-1950; (8 folders) (Box 13, Folder 5-12)
    - Minutes of Executive Committee Meetings, 1950-1959; (14 folders) (Box 13, Folder 13-26)
    - Minutes of Executive Committee Meetings, 1960-1970; (11 folders) (Box 13, Folder 27-37)
    - Minutes of Executive Committee Meetings, Election of Members, 1902-1913 (Box 13, Folder 38)
    - Minutes of Executive Committee Meetings, Election of Members, 1902-1913; (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
    - Minutes, Miscellaneous, 1929, 1940, 1953-1967 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1946, 1966; (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
    - Municipal Art Society Award to Architectural League, 1970 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Nominating Committee (1970), Ulrich Franzen, Chairman (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Non-Profit Mailing, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Notebook (Shorthand), circa 1968-1969 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Notices of Meetings, 1944-1973 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Notices to Executive Committee Members Regarding Meetings, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Position Papers, circa 1966 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - President's Medal to Helen Treadwell, circa 1970 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Prospective Bookkeepers, circa 1968 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Secretary 1933-1934, Minutes and Extracts of All Meetings (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Secretary 1937-1938, Nominations for Executive Committee, Etc. (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Secretary 1938-1939, 1939-1940, Executive Committee, 1938-1940 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Secretary 1938-1939, Nominations for Executive Committee (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Secretary 1939-1940, Minutes of Executive Committee Meetings (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Secretary 1939-1940, New Members Invited to Last Meeting of Old Committee (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Secretary 1941-1942, Executive Committee, 1941-1943 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Secretary 1942-1943, Minutes of Executive Committee Meetings (Extra Copies and Originals) (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Various Membership Lists, circa 1965 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Minutes of Executive Committee Meetings (May 10, 1887 - June 25, 1889), 1887-1889; (Separated materials from Box 11, Folder 22; preservation concern, possible mold) (Box 114, Folder 1)
  - Current Work Committee, 1927-1972; 2.2
    The Current Work Committee oversaw the coordination and organization of exhibitions, events, and functions held by the League. Materials include correspondence, meeting minutes from 1943-1966, committee chairmen's files, schedules of events, scattered exhibition files, and other records related to coordinating events. The Current Work Committee was the first League committee formed in the early 1880s; however, committee records prior to 1927 are not found in this collection. Additional Current Work Committee files are found throughout the collection, especially in the Exhibitions series, Functions and Events series, and Publicity Files series, and are often indicted with the folder heading "Current Work [Year Range]."
    - "Architecture of Speed," Arrangements and Expenses, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - "Before You Buy a House", 1952-1954 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Bills, Robert A.M. Stern, circa 1965-1966 (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Bruce Goff Show (Jan. 22 - Feb. 14, 1970), 1969-1970; (6 folders) (Box 14, Folder 27-32)
    - Budget, 1945-1947, 1967; (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 33-34)
    - Budget Requests, circa 1960s (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - Chairman (Box 14)
      - Abramovitz, Max, 1947-1948; (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 36-37)
      - Bartos, Harold, 1958-1959 (Box 14, Folder 38)
      - Ferriss, Hugh, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 39)
      - Jacobs, Robert Allan, 1949-1950; (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 40-41)
      - Lobell, John, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 42)
      - Magruder, Charles, 1951-1952 (Box 14, Folder 43)
      - Margolies, John S., 1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 44)
      - Rambusch, Viggo, 1944-1948; (3 folders) (Box 14, Folder 45-47)
    - [Chairman], Robert A.M. Stern, 1965-1966 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1936-1972; (19 folders) (Box 15, Folder 2-20)
    - Correspondence, A, L, N, S, 1939; (4 folders) (Box 15, Folder 21-24)